Walter Sullivan Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Walter Sullivan Papers 1929-1997 (bulk 1948-1992)
MSS85555
Sullivan, Walter
75,000 items
214 containers plus 5 oversize
90 linear feet
243 digital files (12.82 MB)
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, lecture files, writings, reviews, wire service reports, notes, book files, alphabetical files, research files, maps, prints, photographs, digital files, and other papers pertaining chiefly to Sullivan’s career as a journalist for the New York Times. Documents his years as a correspondent in China and Antarctica, and his work as a science writer and editor.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Browne, Malcolm W., 1931-2012.; Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957.; Catledge, Turner, 1901-1983.; Clarke, Arthur C. (Arthur Charles), 1917-2008.; Dufek, George J. (George John), 1903-; Rosenthal, A. M. (Abraham Michael), 1922-2006.; Sagan, Carl, 1934-1996.; Siple, Paul, 1908-1968.; Sullivan, Walter.; Sullivan, Walter. Assault on the unknown; the International Geophysical Year. 1961.; Sullivan, Walter. Black holes: the edge of space, the end of time. 1979.; Sullivan, Walter. Continents in motion: the new earth debate. 1974.; Sullivan, Walter. Landprints: on the magnificent American landscape. 1984.; Sullivan, Walter. Quest for a continent: the story of the Antarctic. 1957.; Sullivan, Walter. We are not alone: the search for intelligent life on other worlds. 1964.; Sulzberger, C. L. (Cyrus Leo), 1912-1993.; Weisskopf, Victor Frederick, 1908-2002.
Organizations
American Academy of Arts and Sciences.; National Association of Science Writers.; Operation Deep Freeze.; Operation Highjump (1946-1947); United Nations.; United States. Navy.; Yale University Council.
Subjects
American newspapers--New York (State)--New York.; Astronomy.; Black holes (Astronomy); Climatology.; Cold War.; Cosmology.; Earthquakes.; Geodynamics.; Geophysics--International cooperation.; Human beings--Origin.; International Geophysical Year, 1957-1958.; Korean War, 1950-1953.; Labor--China.; Land reform--China.; Life on other planets.; Oceanography.; Physics.; Planets.; Plate tectonics.; Radioactive wastes.; Science fiction.; Science in mass media.; Science journalism--Antarctica.; Science journalism.; Science news.; Science television programs.; Science--Soviet Union.; Science.; Scientific expeditions--Antarctica.; Seismology.; Telescopes.; Unidentified flying objects.; Volcanoes.; Water.; World politics--1945-1989.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
Places
Alaska.; Antarctica--Discovery and exploration.; China--Commerce.; China--Politics and government--1945-1949.; China--Politics and government--1949-; Germany--Politics and government--1945-1990.; Hawaii.; Korea--Politics and government--20th century.; New Zealand.; Outer space--Exploration.
Titles
New York times.
Occupations
Authors.; Journalists.; Science writers.
Provenance
The papers of Walter Sullivan, science writer, were given to the Library of Congress by his children Elizabeth A. Sullivan, Catherine E. Sullivan, and Theodore L. Sullivan, in 2010.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Videocassettes and vinyl discs have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division. Some maps have been transferred to the Geography and Maps Division. Some books have been transferred to the Rare Books and Special Collections Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Walter Sullivan Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Walter Sullivan are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1918, Jan. 12 Born, New York, N.Y.
1940 BA, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1940 1941 Copy boy, New York Times
1941 1945 United States Naval Reserve, entered as apprentice seaman, exited as Lieutenant Commander
1945 1962 Reporter and correspondent, New York Times
1950 Married Mary Barrett
1958 George Polk Award, special award for coverage of the International Geophysical Year
1962 1964 Science news editor, New York Times
1964 1987 Science editor, New York Times
1965 National Book Award for Non-Fiction, We Are Not Alone: The Search for Intelligent Life on Other Worlds
1973 Charles P. Daly Medal, American Geographical Society
1978 National Science Foundation Distinguished Public Service Award
1980 Public Welfare Medal, National Academy of Sciences
1996, May 19 Died, Riverside, Conn.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Walter Sullivan (1918-1996) span the years 1929 to 1997, with the bulk of the material dating between 1948 and 1992. The papers are organized into the following series: Personal File, Correspondence, Book Files, Newspaper and Magazine Files, Television and Radio Files, Alphabetical Files, Digital Files, and Oversize.
The collection primarily focuses on Sullivan’s work as a writer and science editor at the New York Times. The papers chronicle Sullivan’s coverage of a range of topics including space exploration, plate tectonics, black holes, expeditions to Antarctica, the search for extra-terrestrial intelligence, and the International Geophysical Year. Represented to a lesser extent are materials related to Sullivan’s activities as a lecturer and teacher, and his involvement in television, radio, and film. There is little documentation of Sullivan’s life before becoming a full time reporter at the New York Times in 1945.
The Personal File series comprises documentation of Sullivan’s life and work, mostly between 1950 and 1990. The series includes an extensive collection of Sullivan’s notebooks, expense reports, material related to his lectures, and documentation of his involvement in various professional organizations. In addition to general biographical information, the series includes draft copies of his memoirs, though most of these are available in the Digital Files series.
The Correspondence series primarily includes Sullivan’s incoming letters and is organized into chronological and subject groupings. It spans the period 1948 to 1995, with the bulk of the correspondence concentrated between 1957 and 1989 when he was most active in writing about science. The files consist mostly of professional correspondence and internal New York Times memoranda. In many cases, correspondence files exist in other series as they relate to specific projects, especially within the Book Files series.
The largest series of the collection, the Book Files comprise materials related to the books in which Sullivan was author, editor, and contributor. The bulk of the file focuses on his six major publications: Quest for a Continent: The Story of the Antarctic (1957), Assault on the Unknown; the International Geophysical Year (1961), We Are Not Alone: The Search for Intelligent Life on Other Worlds (1964; revised 1993), Continents in Motion: The New Earth Debate (1974; revised 1991), Black Holes: The Edge of Space, the End of Time (1979), and Landprints: On the Magnificent American Landscape (1984). The files primarily include research files, drafts, correspondence, and book artwork. Additional research materials related to the topics explored in the books are also filed in the Alphabetical Files series.
The Newspaper and Magazine Files series primarily comprises materials related to Sullivan’s career as a correspondent and science editor at the New York Times. These include clippings of published articles and raw copy of articles written by Sullivan for the New York Times and various magazines and journals. Most files feature topics related to science with the exception of files focusing on political issues in China, Korea, and Germany in the late 1940s and early 1950s when Sullivan was working as a foreign correspondent in those countries.
The Television and Radio Files series comprises materials related to Sullivan’s involvement and appearances on television and radio programs, mostly from the early 1960s to 1990. The bulk of the series focuses on the unproduced television program “Landprints,” based on Sullivan’s 1984 book of the same title. Additional files related to Sullivan’s television appearances between 1975 and 1990 are located in the Personal File series.
The Alphabetical Files series contains research files regarding a wide range of subjects, individuals, publications, organizations, and projects related to scientific topics featured in Sullivan's writings. The material ranges from 1929 to 1995, with the majority of the files dating between 1950 and 1990.
The Digital Files series consists of digital files stored on floppy disks and mostly includes text files created by Sullivan from the early 1980s to 1993. Memoir drafts and raw copy of articles represent the majority of the files. Also included are correspondence, estate and trustee information, and files related to the television program “Landprints.”
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in eight series:
Personal File, 1932-1996
Correspondence, 1948-1995
Book Files, 1934-1997
Newspaper and Magazine Files, 1938-1995
Television and Radio Files, 1951-1993
Alphabetical Files, 1929-1995
Digital Files, 1980-1993
Oversize, 1932-1984
Container List
- Personal File, 1932-1996 (Box 1-19)
  Materials related to Sullivan’s life and work. The lecture materials form a significant portion of this series and primarily comprise notes and logistics for speaking appearances, mostly facilitated by the Keedick Lecture Bureau. Sullivan’s lecture subjects include continental drift, science in the twenty-first century, the search for extra-terrestrial intelligence, black holes, Mars, Antarctica, and in-vitro fertilization. Detailed expense reports provide a record of Sullivan’s travels and assignments while covering stories for the New York Times. The files regarding professional organizations and committees mostly document Sullivan’s involvement in the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, National Association of Science Writers, and Yale University Council. The series also contains materials related to seminars and workshops taught by Sullivan on the search for extra-terrestrial intelligence, science writing, and technology and social change. Sullivan’s experience in the Navy during World War II is detailed primarily in his draft memoirs. The notebooks contain handwritten notes related to articles, books, and other projects. However, most are undated. There is little to no documentation of Sullivan’s education or family life.
  Writings, correspondence, notebooks, clippings, awards, certificates, biographical material, lecture notes, photographs, reports, schedules, itineraries.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material
  - Archives, 1966-1968, 1979, 1983 See also Digital Files, Archives, Byrd Polar Research Center, Ohio State University, Columbus, Ohio (Box 1)
  - Awards, 1957-1959, 1965-1967, 1974, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Biographical file, 1950, 1959-1974, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Expenses (Box 1)
    - 1938-1946, 1963-1981, (9 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1982-1991, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Fat Man and Little Boy (movie), 1988-1990, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Fellowships, 1977-1979, 1985-1990 (Box 2)
  - Fellowships and seminars, Yale University, New Haven, Conn., 1969, 1976-1980, 1988-1989, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Groton School, Mass., 1957-1962 (Box 3)
  - Higley copper coin reproduction, undated (Box 3)
  - Lectures (Box 3)
    - Antarctica, 1990-1993, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Chronological file (Box 3)
      - 1957-1958, (3 folders) (Box 3)
      - 1959-1967, (9 folders) (Box 4)
      - 1968-1974, 1991-1992, (9 folders) (Box 5)
      - 1993-1996, undated, (4 folders) (Box 6)
    - "Energy 2020," 1978-1979, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - "Landprints," 1974-1976, 1985-1986 (Box 6)
    - Miscellany, 1962-1978, 1984-1995, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Notes (Box 7)
      - Antarctic; black holes; International Geophysical Year, 1957-1958; public understanding of science; tectonics, 1969, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
      - Covering science; physics; science and the public; Ives introduction, undated (Box 7)
      - "Hopes and Fears in the Year 2000," undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
      - "Hopes and Fears in the Year 2000"; robots, undated (Box 7)
      - "Hopes and Fears in the Year 2000"; "What Makes Habitable Planets Habitable?"; man's survival, undated (Box 7)
      - Miscellany, 1970-1971, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
      - "We Are Not Alone"; space cosmology, undated, (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - Posters, 1932-1936, 1965, undated See also Container OV 2, same title (Box 8)
    - Siam, 1981, undated (Box 8)
    - Slides (Box 8)
      - Antarctica, 1956-1958, 1976-1978, undated (Box 8)
      - Black holes, 1978, undated (Box 8)
      - Communication with extraterrestrial intelligence, undated (Box 8)
      - Energy, 1979, undated (Box 8)
      - "Landprints," 1978-1982, undated (Box 9)
      - Leonardo da Vinci and Chinese technology, undated (Box 9)
      - Mars (planet), 1965, 1986, undated (Box 9)
      - Miscellany, 1974, 1978, undated (Box 9)
      - Oasis expedition, 1979, undated (Box 9)
      - Panama, undated (Box 9)
    - Tectonic illustrations, undated (Box 9)
    - Titanic (steamship), 1986, undated (Box 9)
    - Topics, undated (Box 9)
  - Lectures and television See also Television and Radio Files, Miscellaneous television shows and scripts (Box 9)
    - 1975-1978 See also Container OV 3, same title, (6 folders) (Box 9)
    - 1979-1982, (6 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1983-1988, (9 folders) (Box 11)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 12)
  - Memberships and committees (Box 12)
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1968-1973, 1983-1984, 1993-1995, (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - American Geographical Society, 1932, 1959-1962, 1972-1995 (Box 12)
    - American Institute of Physics, 1961-1968 (Box 12)
    - American Physical Society, 1986-1988, undated (Box 12)
    - American Polar Society, 1974-1989, 1995 (Box 12)
    - American Tentative Society, 1989-1992 (Box 12)
    - Arctic Institute of North America, 1961-1966, 1973-1978, 1987-1988 (Box 12)
    - Century Association, 1987-1994, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - General Motors Cancer Research Foundation, 1989-1990 (Box 13)
    - Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., committees, 1973-1979 (Box 13)
    - Miscellany, 1965-1990 See also Container OV 3, same title (Box 13)
    - National Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1971, 1980, 1987-1989, 1995 (Box 13)
    - National Association of Science Writers, 1959-1960, 1966, 1984-1995, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - New York Academy of Sciences, 1972, 1990-1996 (Box 13)
    - New York Museum of Science and Technology, New York, N.Y., 1960-1969 (Box 13)
    - Princeton University, Princeton, N.J., Department of Geological and Geophysical Sciences Advisory Council, 1970-1977, 1990 (Box 14)
    - Public Affairs Committee, 1967-1968, 1981 (Box 14)
    - Pugwash Conferences on Science and World Affairs, 1962, 1969, 1987 (Box 14)
    - Yale University Council, Yale University, New Haven, Conn., 1965-1982, 1989-1995, undated, (6 folders) (Box 14)
  - Memoir drafts, undated See also Digital Files, same title (Box 15)
  - New York Times payment receipts, 1960-1962 (Box 15)
  - New York Times stockholder meetings, 1961, 1974 (Box 15)
  - Notebooks (Box 15)
    - 1957-1963, 1970-1971, undated, (7 folders) (Box 15)
    - undated, (6 folders); (4 folders); (5 folders); (1 folder) (Box 16, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19)
  - Photographs of Sullivan, 1964-1974, undated, (4 folders) (Box 19)
  - Royalty statements, 1973-1974 (Box 19)
  - Schedule and address books, 1957-1959 (Box 19)
  - Seminar on Technology and Social Change, Columbia University, New York, N.Y., 1978-1982, 1988 (Box 19)
  - Teaching jobs, 1969, 1979-1985 (Box 19)
  - Virgin Islands, 1968-1984, 1994-1995 (Box 19)
  - Workshop in Writing: "Writing about Science," Princeton University, Princeton, N.J., 1987-1988 (Box 19)
- Correspondence, 1948-1995 (Box 19-66)
  This series comprises letters among Sullivan, colleagues, friends, and leaders in various scientific fields including Victor Frederick Weisskopf, Carl Sagan, and Arthur C. Clarke. Many relate to his professional career as an author, lecturer, and science editor and correspondent for the New York Times. Also includes letters from readers, fans, individuals seeking employment, and many unsolicited articles, essays, and opinion pieces submitted to Sullivan in his capacity as science editor. Memoranda at the New York Times document Sullivan’s role as science editor and include interactions with staff members Turner Catledge, A. M. Rosenthal, C. L. Sulzberger, and Malcolm W. Browne. Subject files contain letters and memoranda from when Sullivan was traveling or on assignment, letters from publishers, and materials related to science coverage. In keeping with the original order, incoming and outgoing letters with individual correspondents are oftentimes grouped together and filed according to the date of the most recent letter. There is no family correspondence in the collection.
  Letters, memoranda, itineraries, wire reports, telegrams, cables, invitations, postcards, and various attachments.
  Arranged chronologically within a chronological file and alphabetically within a subject file
  - Chronological file See also Digital Files, same title (Box 19)
    - 1948-1956, (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - 1957-1958, (9 folders) (Box 20)
    - 1959, Jan.-1959, Oct., (11 folders) (Box 21)
    - 1959, Nov.-1961, Apr., (10 folders) (Box 22)
    - 1961, May-1962, May, (9 folders) (Box 23)
    - 1962, June-1964, Dec., (11 folders) (Box 24)
    - 1965, Jan.-1966, Apr., (9 folders) (Box 25)
    - 1966, May-1966, Sept., (7 folders) (Box 26)
    - 1966, Sept.-1966, Dec., (7 folders) (Box 27)
    - 1967, Jan.-1967, Aug., (9 folders) (Box 28)
    - 1967, Sept.-1968, May, (9 folders) (Box 29)
    - 1968, June-1969, Jan., (9 folders) (Box 30)
    - 1969, Feb.-1969, Aug., (7 folders) (Box 31)
    - 1969, Sept.-1970, Mar., (8 folders) (Box 32)
    - 1970, Apr.-1971, Jan., (7 folders) (Box 33)
    - 1971, Feb.-1971, July, (7 folders) (Box 34)
    - 1971, Aug.-1972, Feb., (8 folders) (Box 35)
    - 1972, Mar.-1972, July, (7 folders) (Box 36)
    - 1972, Aug.-1973, Jan., (9 folders) (Box 37)
    - 1973, Feb.-1973, Aug., (9 folders) (Box 38)
    - 1973, Sept.-1973, Dec., (5 folders) (Box 39)
    - 1974 (Box 39)
      - A, (2 folders) (Box 39)
      - B-H, (8 folders) (Box 40)
      - I-R, (9 folders) (Box 41)
      - S-Z, (7 folders) (Box 42)
    - 1975 (Box 43)
      - A-H, (7 folders) (Box 43)
      - H-R, (9 folders) (Box 44)
      - S-Z, (4 folders) (Box 45)
    - 1976 (Box 45)
      - A-F, (5 folders) (Box 45)
      - G-R, (11 folders) (Box 46)
      - S-Z, (4 folders) (Box 47)
    - 1977 (Box 47)
      - A-G, (5 folders) (Box 47)
      - H-Z, (10 folders) (Box 48)
    - 1978, Jan.-1978, July, (9 folders) (Box 49)
    - 1978, Aug.-1979, May, (9 folders) (Box 50)
    - 1979, June-1980, Mar., (9 folders) (Box 51)
    - 1980, Apr.-1981, Mar., (10 folders) (Box 52)
    - 1981, Apr.-1982, Mar., (11 folders) (Box 53)
    - 1982, Apr.-1983, Feb., (10 folders) (Box 54)
    - 1983, Mar.-1984, Jan., (11 folders) (Box 55)
    - 1984, Feb.-1984, Sept., (9 folders) (Box 56)
    - 1984, Oct.-1985, Mar., (7 folders) (Box 57)
    - 1985, Apr.-1985, Dec., (9 folders) (Box 58)
    - 1986, Jan.-1986, July, (8 folders) (Box 59)
    - 1986, Aug.-1987, June, (10 folders) (Box 60)
    - 1987, July-1988, Aug., (10 folders) (Box 61)
    - 1988, Sept.-1989, Nov., (9 folders) (Box 62)
    - 1991, 1994-1995, (2 folders) (Box 62)
    - Undated, (1 folder); (4 folders) (Box 62, Box 63)
  - Subject file (Box 63)
    - Antarctica trip, 1976 (Box 63)
    - Col de Fenêtre hike, 1968 (Box 63)
    - Doubleday (publisher), 1973-1982 (Box 63)
    - Europe (Box 63)
      - 1968-1988, undated, (2 folders) (Box 63)
      - 1972-1976, 1982, (3 folders) (Box 64)
    - Fan mail, 1957-1963, (2 folders) (Box 64)
    - Ingersoll and Brennan (literary agents), and various publishers, 1947-1964, (2 folders) (Box 64)
    - McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1955-1963, 1974-1975, (3 folders) (Box 64)
    - McGraw-Hill Book Company and Macmillan London, 1974-1978 (Box 65)
    - New York Times, 1954-1955 (Box 65)
    - New York Times interdepartmental memoranda, 1974-1977, (3 folders) (Box 65)
    - Operation Deep Freeze messages, 1956-1957 (Box 65)
    - Paranoia, 1974-1975 (Box 65)
    - Science coverage, 1958-1987, undated, (1 folder); (3 folders) (Box 65, Box 66)
    - Soviet Union trips, 1961-1962, 1983-1987 (Box 66)
    - Travel and itineraries, 1957-1961 (Box 66)
    - Trip meetings and memoranda, 1964 (Box 66)
    - USS Atka (AGB-3), 1956 (Box 66)
- Book Files, 1934-1997 (Box 66-127)
  This series comprises drafts, research files, book reviews, and marketing, advertising, and promotional materials, mostly for books authored by Sullivan. Correspondence in these files includes letters from subject matter experts who edited or reviewed drafts of manuscripts, permissions for book illustrations and art, and correspondence with publishers. The most documented books are Continents in Motion and Landprints, both of which contain extensive research files. Additional research files associated with Landprints are available in the Television and Radio Files series, which includes files regarding an unproduced television program of the same name. The files related to Quest for a Continent include many of the primary sources Sullivan accumulated during his early Antarctic expeditions, including files on Operation Highjump, and correspondence with Richard Evelyn Byrd, Paul Siple, and George J. Dufek. The files for We Are Not Alone contain many research files on the origin of human life and the search for extra-terrestrial intelligence. Book files featuring Sullivan as contributor include encyclopedia entries and essays on topics including physics, the International Geophysical Year, science fiction, and science in the Soviet Union. At the top of the series is an administrative file documenting contracts, sales figures, book projects, and publisher information.
  Writings, correspondence, illustrations, photographs, posters, maps, galley proofs, research files, reviews, clippings, notes, contracts.
  Arranged alphabetically by book title or topic
  - Administrative file (Box 66)
    - Book contracts, 1965-1972, 1982-1983 (Box 66)
    - Book projects, 1964-1986, (2 folders) (Box 66)
    - Book sales, 1974-1975, 1989 (Box 66)
    - Publishers, 1990, undated (Box 66)
  - America's Race for the Moon, editor, 1970-1978, 1987-1992 (Box 66)
  - Assault on the Unknown; the International Geophysical Year (Box 66)
    - Corrections, 1961-1962, undated (Box 66)
    - Correspondence, 1959-1962, (4 folders) (Box 67)
    - Miscellany, 1961-1965, undated (Box 67)
    - Photographs and illustrations
      - 1956-1960, (2 folders) (Box 67)
      - 1956-1965, undated See also Container OV 2, same title, (2 folders) (Box 68)
    - Reviews, 1961-1962 (Box 68)
  - Black Holes: The Edge of Space, the End of Time (Box 68)
    - Addresses for mailing, 1973-1979 (Box 68)
    - Advertisements and promotion, 1979-1985 (Box 68)
    - Art captions, circa 1978 (Box 68)
    - Chapter checking, 1977-1978, (2 folders) (Box 68)
    - Corrections, 1979-1980, undated (Box 68)
    - Doubleday memoranda, 1974-1978 (Box 68)
    - Draft, undated, (1 folder) (Box 68, Box 69)
    - Final revisions, 1977-1978 (Box 69)
    - Galley proofs, undated (Box 69)
    - Gifts, 1977-1980 (Box 69)
    - Permissions, 1978-1979, (2 folders) (Box 69)